so hi my name is Joe brewer and I'm a
change strategist what I want to talk
with you about today is what I think of
as a very big problem or a significant
challenge that we have to address and
that challenge is how do we know who to
trust and how can we be sure that export
information is actually reliable in
today's world where we have a number of
people that for ideological reasons are
actively fighting against scientific
expertise we have a world where some
scientists orbit arrogant and opposed to
considering the views or the expertise
of different kinds of people such as
spiritual leaders or political leaders
and of course we have this public
relations nightmare of companies that
are set up specifically to actively
confuse people about the science is a
huge huge challenge for us because the
big complex problems in the world can
only be solved if we have reliable
legitimate information so the book that
I want to review that explores this
topic in a very unique way is this one
are we all scientific experts now by
Kerry Collins well first of all Harry
Collins he is a social theorist so he's
one of the founders of the field of
sociology of science so a few decades
ago earlier in his career he spent a lot
of time criticizing science taking it
down from its pedestal of being special
in the world of knowledge and showing it
human or that science is a human
endeavor filled with all of the folly
and FAL a valley ability the frailty of
the human condition and then what
happened was based on his work and the
work of other sociologists studying the
scientific method we came to a place
where people in the humanities were
criticizing science so much that they
had all but destroyed any of its
uniqueness and so people were just say
well if you have an opinion about
science doesn't matter if you've studied
in a field of research for 20 years it's
merely you an opinion and it's no
different from my opinion based on
reading a 200-word paragraph on a blog
post that made me upset so now your
expertise is totally illegitimate and I
don't really care about it one a place
where that level of extreme
vism his way to a common place so what
Hilary Collins did coming back after all
of those decades of work and looking at
the practices of science and the kinds
of knowledge that people develop in
science came back and wrote this short
see it's very small it's a short easy to
read book it's actually very accessible
to the layperson and what he does is he
tries to make the case that maybe he
went too far and that the other social
theorists criticizing science have also
gone way too far and that science is
actually special and important in a
couple of very specific ways that only
people studying the sociology of science
understand so he answers his own
question no we are decidedly not all
scientific experts now but the only way
for us to know who the experts are and
what the important kinds of expertise
maybe is to systematically go through
and answer the question what are the
different kinds of expertise and so sure
there are types of knowledge or
technical expertise if I get a PhD in
high-energy particle physics I'm going
to understand quantum mechanics I'm
going to understand things about
chemistry about certain instrumentation
that I use but there's another kind of
expertise in addition to this that he
makes the case for being extremely
important and that is the expertise in
social knowledge of the people involved
and the people the reputations of those
people so I am a climate scientist and
I'm engaged in research with a hundred
other climate scientists I know which
one of those which of those scientists
are good-hearted well-meaning
hard-working honest people I know which
ones are kind of the crackpots that you
don't really trust that no one really
pays attention to because all of us
climate scientists know that their work
is on the margins so there's kind of
social knowledge in context for people
who are actively involved in a community
turns out that that kind of knowledge is
one of the most important kinds of
knowledge for determining whether
scientific expertise is valid or not so
if you're questioning the health
outcomes of a particular study as a
layperson you don't know if the
researchers involved are credible or not
because you're not part of the
munity of practice in that particular
field of science but the people who are
in that field of science have that
social expertise and so they can discern
who's trustworthy and who is it turns
out this is true for all of us in every
domain of practice but it's something
that we really need to appreciate in the
world of technical knowledge because
that is where the social layer of
contextual knowledge becomes so
important so if you want to better
understand how to see the different
kinds of expertise make sense of which
scientists are valid and whether what
they're saying is legitimate or not pick
up a copy of this book and then explore
how it applies to all forms of
authoritative knowledge expertise and
legitimate knowledge and then you will
be better armed to go out into the world
and discern who you can trust what
information you can trust and then act
accordingly so there you go Harry
Collins are we all like scientific
experts now go grab your copy